I believe up next we have.
Yes, Mónica and Doctor Raffel.
Take it away.
Yeah. Thank you.
Just let me do this.
Screen share.
Yay! Thank you so much,
everyone, for coming.
So today we are going to talk about
translation and localization
of visual novels,
specifically the Ace Attorney series
from the perspective of the Latino Ace
Attorney fandom.
And so to start, I'm going to talk
a little bit about some background y.
And you can go to the next slide.
Monica so we're going to start
with some sort of background
on why we would classify
visual novels as illiterate.
Some sort of considerations
that we've found in the literature
of why translating elit is
maybe more complicated than translating
other forms of literature,
and why that extends to visual novels.
And then some examples of
why of how that's manifested
in translating Ace Attorney,
some examples of how people have
translated that, and some different fan
groups who have kind of taken
the lack of official localizations
into their own hands.
So to start.
Sorry, I'm getting message
that my internet connection is unstable,
so hopefully it is fine.
But so to start, we wanted to make sure
that we could
that we could situate or situate
visual novels
into the sort of umbrella of lit.
So we went back to going back
to Catherine
Hale's definition, looking at eyelid
as something that's digital born
and something that's usually created
and meant to be read on a computer.
And that sort of very visual novels
very much fall into this basic definition.
But of course, Hayles goes on to say
that things with too many game elements
maybe we wouldn't classify
as visual novels, but one of the things
that we sort of looked at
was that many visual novels are reflexive,
and a lot of them, such as
novels like Doki Doki Literature Club,
have aspects that that make
you think about the format
and think about the platform,
and to us, that puts them
solidly under this umbrella of eyelets.
They sometimes make you go back
and go into the files of the game,
even to obtain specific endings.
And so when we're thinking of Ace
Attorney, it's also very procedural
in the fact that it deals
with a lot of courtroom procedure.
And it's and it's
sort of reflexive in that way
and also very linguistically punny.
And that's one of the challenges
that we'll talk about as we talk about why
translating and localizing
it is a little bit,
maybe more difficult
than the average work of literature.
Let's see.
So continuing on to kind of situate
what we're talking about, we're talking
about translation and localization
when we discuss visual novels.
So translation by itself
is usually just the adjustment of text
to another language.
Whereas localization needs
to consider cultural contexts.
And because this series is so,
uses plays on words and uses
things like courtroom,
courtroom language and law language,
there needs to be cultural contexts
so that the new audience
and the new culture can understand
what's going on in the game, but also
so that the game can kind of preserve
the lighthearted, fun
linguistic aspects
that people love it for.
And then continuing on,
when we talk about translating Illit
specifically,
there's been some work done in this area
for translating for different languages.
And so we look at
why Illit is so unique in its translation,
and that's because of its reflexivity.
So we have to pay attention
to the code of the work
and the platform of the work,
and then you know the
how the code and platform then interact
with the the semantics of the text.
And that's why Mirek and Montfort
identify that the translator of Illit
kind of ends up becoming an ambassador
of the work for the new audience.
And in many situations, that's kind of
what the fan translators have done.
And we'll show you
kind of how they do that on social media,
how they sort of make sure their works
are seen by the audience
that they're translating for,
and also how they kind of
as fans and advocates
for these translations, make them happen
and, and, and use kind of a hashtag
activism to make that happen.
So moving on.
We have seen in the literature
that fan trends,
when fans translate,
they can kind of engage
in this transcultural literacy,
and it becomes a
this becomes a way
in which the process itself
becomes important,
not just the end product of translation.
So not only is this fan translation
reaching a new audience, right?
The people who are doing
the translation is using these
what Shaffer calls these playful trans
linguistic
and cultural resources
and reflecting on cultural differences.
So the reflexive process itself
becomes important in fan translation
and in reaching
and thinking about which communities
are kind of affected by the translation.
Whereas in the official translation,
sometimes there can be a tendency
to ignore cultural
and that can that can cause, as Edwards
defines, that can cause a difficulty
with gamers potentially engaging
with the content at the
at a deep, meaningful level, at the level
at which they want to
engage with the content, because they've
sometimes played the game in English,
but would like to play the game
in this case in their native either
Latin American, Spanish
or Portuguese language.
And there I will hand it off
to Monica,
who's going to talk about some examples.
Awesome.
So the track record
for the official localization,
as far as ignoring cultural,
especially when producing for Hispanic
audiences, has been consistent,
except for when it came
to the handling of Hispanic
or Latino coded characters.
Case in point we have characters
like Juan who's here on the slide,
who is the only character
in the second game that is Latino coded
where he is name
just kind of like turns into Rivera
in a defunct European Spanish
localization due to the term corrida
being a considered crass
in the Spain community.
This continues on into the following
installment
in the series, where the other Latina
Hispanic coded character, the Armando
his name gets
in the future changed into Yago Dorigo
in the more
recent localization patch
that came out as of November 2025.
Due to the fact that
the name Diego has a strong.
Tied to,
you know, in Latin American communities,
we associate the name Diego Armando
with football player Diego Maradona.
So in order to kind
of just like differentiate,
then official
localizer switch these names over,
which, you know, like
considering that these previous patches
would only do this
for the Latino communities
as opposed to just doing full
localizations of every name, you know,
we start to see a pattern now,
official translations
by the original developer
are not always supported,
and they may become available
and unavailable
throughout the series life cycle.
And thus these translations
and localizations of visual novels
are often conducted by individuals
with minimal translation experience.
As has been the case with this franchise.
Technical communication
literature has identified challenges
with this practice,
where technical documents that
when technical documents are concerned,
these practitioners may be expected
to create translations and localizations
without being trained in the field,
which is an issue that could extend
to fan translations on both visual novels.
Elit, where, you know,
there's a technical procedure
that must also be considered now,
like rights, that instead of being viewing
less experienced serious leaders
as a pitfall, fan
translation actually serves more purpose
than simply just
adjusting the text into another language
for others to access.
They suggest that there is not only value
in the outcome of making fan translation,
you know, in translation in general more
accessible despite it being unsupported
and supervised
in the context of unsupervised translation
of the series,
we observe a nature of collaboration
in which we have professional translators
collaborating with translations to the s
that produce patches to provide
that will provide better representation,
such as the case with
the team behind AA Spanish translations,
where official licensed
translator Milagros Hart from Argentina
is contributing with amateur translators
to provide a Latino Spanish fan
translation of one of the spin off
games in the series.
Her contribution is exceptional
because we see somebody who has judicial
and media experience
in official localization,
collaborating with amateurs,
similar cases we've seen
within the Brazilian Portuguese community,
where we see teams like the jacket
themes about fan translation team,
which became the primary source
of Portuguese language
fan patches for the community
up until the release
of the most recent official
trilogy localization patch
that came out in November 2025.
Now, none of this progress has come
without its efforts, and
through the years, we've observed
the hashtag activism for fan communities
requesting wide release of Spanish
localization by using the hashtag protest
attorney and hashtag
No Spanish, often accompanied by
means created by using in-game
content or references
alluding to the lack of language options
and even working QR codes.
Distributing fully operational patch
versions of the original trilogy.
In conclusion, the efforts of fans
to translate the Ace Attorney franchise
and other visual novels
in the absence of official localizations
can provide insight to the participatory
and sometimes unsupervised practice
of translating electronic literature
more widely.
As part of these localizations,
themes of fans must consider
linguistic differences, have social
and cultural awareness, find creative ways
to distribute and promote their work,
and be aware of the interactive nature
of electronic texts.
Though not all fans
may have traditional education
in translation and localization.
Examining how communities come together
in support of translation
can help us understand its importance
as an ambassador of
sometimes a recognized works
that can otherwise have limited reach.
Thank you.